<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="task_smw_dhg_23">
    <title>Advantages of using DITA for policy and procedure documents</title>
    <shortdesc>Many companies have a vast number of documents, many of which have significantly
        overlapping concepts. Efforts to write a policy or procedure the traditional ("bottom down")
        way can be thwarted by questions like “where does this information really belong?” It’s a
        question that just goes away when you can reassemble a document using a disposable map, then
        assemble another manual later using some of the same bits.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
        <author>John Gordon Tait</author>
        <copyright>
            <copyryear year="2012"/>
            <copyrholder>John Gordon Tait</copyrholder>
        </copyright>
    </prolog>
    <taskbody>
        
        <section>
            <p>Specific subject areas can fundamentally cut across disciplines. For example,
                engineering standards can be presented according to the asset owner, or the asset
                lifecycle, or from a systems view, or from the perspective of risk. None of these is
                definitively better than another. It would be a simple (very big, but simple)
                exercise to cut this kind of material up and reassemble it cleanly into manuals
                using DITA.</p>
            <p>The point is this you <i>don't</i> need to know in advance how to best present it,
                and you can change your mind. Or, if you team or organisation changes and has
                different priorities, you can create a new map without rewriting (much). </p>
            <p>Most reference works to DITA have a slant towards localisation and translation costs.
                Localisation and translation isn’t usually of interest when writing policy and
                procedure documents. Other DITA reference works expect the content to be in the
                genre of product information, where DITA’s core support and communities seems to
                reside. </p>
            <p>I personally suspect that there a vast underworld of unmaintained policy and
                procedure documents in lots of big companies and government organisations that I
                think a structured approach could make a real diference to.</p>
            <p>DITA is actually designed as a general purpose information interchange format.
                Structured documents is just one of the things it can be applied to. It is probably
                the most future-proof format you can write documents in, and is a safe format for
                long-lived documents.</p>
            <p>DITA has three, powerful features that make it worth considering.<ul
                    id="ul_uqy_2mf_l3">
                    <li>Documents can be assembled from smaller parts called <i>topics</i>. This
                        feature is hardly unique to DITA, but DITA has been explicitly designed to
                        support it. Documents are built up in a clean way using <i>maps</i> from a
                        selection of your topics, and can include other smaller <i>maps</i> as
                        well.</li>
                    <li>Selections from the maps can be filtered in or out in a technique called
                            <i>conditional profiling.</i> Again, this isn't at all unique to DITA.
                        There are three general ways to approach this, all of them useful:<ol
                            id="ol_tsz_xmf_l3">
                            <li>You can display only certain pieces of text in a custom document
                                aimed at a particular audience (or other profiling attribute). You
                                do this by hiding all the text aimed at different audiences then
                                pulling forward the text aimed at the audience you want. This allows
                                you to produce multiple documents from a single map.</li>
                            <li>You can just hide text aimed at audiences you want to miss out.</li>
                            <li>You can flag up (display an image or use a particular piece of text
                                beside) text aimed at a particular audience. This is useful if you
                                want to produce a general document that different audiences can use
                                easily.</li>
                        </ol></li>
                    <li>You can pull text from other topics into your topics using <i>content
                            references</i> or <i>conrefs</i>. This is very powerful and is probably
                        DITA's killer feature. (The technical word for this is "transclusion".)
                        Transcluded text is much neater and help than just cutting and pasting
                        because, if the transcluded text changes, all instances where the text
                        appears will change too. </li>
                </ul></p>
        </section>
    </taskbody>
</task>
