<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="task_smw_dhg_23">
    <title>Advantages of using DITA for policy and procedure documents</title>
    <shortdesc>Many companies have a vast number of documents, many of which have significantly
        overlapping concepts. Efforts to write a policy or procedure the traditional ("bottom down")
        way can be thwarted by questions like “where does this information really belong?” It’s a
        question that just goes away when you can reassemble a document using a disposable map, then
        assemble another manual later using some of the same bits.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
        <author>John Gordon Tait</author>
        <copyright>
            <copyryear year="2012"/>
            <copyrholder>John Gordon Tait</copyrholder>
        </copyright>
    </prolog>
    <taskbody>
        
        <section>
            <p>Specific subject areas can fundamentally cut across disciplines. For example,
                engineering standards can be presented according to the asset owner, or the asset
                lifecycle, or from a systems view, or from the perspective of risk. None of these is
                definitively better than another. It would be a simple (very big, but simple)
                exercise to cut this kind of material up and reassemble it cleanly into manuals
                using DITA.</p>
            <p>The point is this you know need to know in advance how to best present it, and you
                can change your mind. Or, if you team or organisation changes and has different
                priorities, you can create a new map without rewriting (much). </p>
            <p>Most reference works to DITA have a slant towards localisation and translation costs.
                Localisation and translation isn’t usually of interest when writing policy and
                procedure documents. Other DITA reference works expects the content to be in the
                genre of product information, where DITA’s core support seems to reside. </p>
            <p>I personally suspect that there a vast underworld of unmaintained policy and
                procedure documents in lots of big companies and government organisations that I
                know DITA could make a real difference with.</p>
            <p>DITA is actually designed as a general purpose information interechange format.
                Structured documents is just one of the things it can currently do. It is probably
                the most future-proof format you can write documents in, and is a safe format for
                long-lived documents.</p>
        </section>
    </taskbody>
</task>
