<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="task_afk_41x_f3">
    <title>Cross-referencing content, knowledge management implications of managing section numbering and other kinds of
        sequential numbering</title>
    <titlealts>
        <navtitle>Cross-referencing content and numbering</navtitle>
    </titlealts>
    <shortdesc>Most policy and procedure documents are extensively numbered. This provides for
        simple cross-referencing, but creates a massive overhead for maintainability of the whole
        document and, particularly, reuse of the smaller parts in other related documents. Without
        numbering, or where final numbering isn't going to be available to you as an author, focus
        on the names of elements you will refer to and reference those.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
        <author>John Gordon Tait</author>
        <copyright>
            <copyryear year="2012"/>
            <copyrholder>John Gordon Tait</copyrholder>
        </copyright>
    </prolog>
    <taskbody>
        <section>
            <p>There is an obvious cost in ease of reference for particular sections. This might
                cause some difficulty with claiming compliance with particular sections.</p>
            <p>There seems to be no real reason why DITA processing tools could not provide optional
                numbering on the output, but this doesn't seem to be a priority.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Refer to cross-referenced tables and figures by their name</title>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Give tables and figures useful, long, unique names</title>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What to conref</title>
            <p>You can conref whole <codeph>section</codeph> elements. This probably isn't te
                canonical way of using conrefs, because the computer documentation tradition seems
                to require much more of the alteration of sentence and meaning rather than pulling
                whole paragraphs across.</p>
            <p>For standards, this mechanism allows simple and predictable transclusion for smallish
                packets of text, with might or might not have titles.</p>
            <p>Conref <codeph>phrase</codeph> elements.</p>
            <p><codeph>Resource-only</codeph> attribute</p>
        </section>
    </taskbody>
</task>
