<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_gpb_hwf_23">
 <title>About this book</title>
 <shortdesc>Structured documents provide the best, simplest and most reliable tools to write policy and procedure documents.</shortdesc>
 <prolog>
  <author>John Gordon Tait</author>
  <copyright>
   <copyryear year="2012"/>
   <copyrholder>John Gordon Tait</copyrholder>
  </copyright>
 </prolog>
 <conbody>
  <p>This book is written for someone writing or managing policy and procedure documents, and
   standards documents of any kind. (I will use these terms interchangeably.)</p>
  <p>These documents are usually managed by small dedicated teams. The content comes from experts in
   their fields. These subject matter experts usually don't care too much about documentation
   because their expertise lies in other areas.</p>
  <p>Standards are designed to be <i>complied</i> with, or they specify that a process or item
    <i>conforms</i> to it. They are usually written as instructions, or might use the words "shall"
   and "should" to specify a requirement or guidance, respectively.</p>
  <p>It is the nature of this type of work to go out of date as organisations and roles change, and
   new processes need documented. Because standards are complex (made of many parts) and complicated
   (full of specialist technical material), maintaining these documents is difficult and time
   consuming.</p>
  <p>Standards can have multiple authors for their different parts, and the different parts can be
   updated at different times. The entire document will usually need to be reviewed formally by
   multiple stakeholders, and their comments somehow incorporated into this complex document.</p>
  <p>To help navigate these documents, they usually contain cross-references to other parts of the
   document. These cross-references will themselves need to be updated manually, or at least checked
   manually because, as different authors add and remove different sections, there to no guarantee
   that the document will still hang together. Cross-references, while useful to the reader, also
   bring their own burden of page-turning and sense-making.</p>
  <p>Standards documents are also usually part of a wider set or family of other documents which can
   cite each other using references. Standards authors will need to check these each time.
   References <i>to</i> other standards can be checked by following the reference, and refererence
    <i>from</i> other standards will require some knowledge of the subject matter.</p>
  <p>Standards processes work because they are collaborative and tested with their stakeholders. But
   the traditional processes for developing them is labour intensive and prone to mistakes without a
   diligent manager and editorial team.</p>
  <p>Can the technology and technique called DITA help? Well, perhaps.</p>
  <p>There are some very real advantages to trying DITA for this purpose, and some real problems. If
   you are involved in managing standards, I think it could be well worth trying, but the existing
   literature seems to be written by<ul id="ul_tdm_4xr_h3">
    <li>originators and implementators of the DITA specification, who are perhaps not aware of the
     specific needs of <i>standards</i> authors</li>
    <li>consultants of various kinds, who might quite naturally emphasise some of the benefits and
     less of the disadvantages, and who also might try to solve unnecessary technical problems</li>
    <li>technical writers in the specific fields of product documentation and, more especially,
     computer software documentation. This is a quite different genre from standards. These writers
     might be focussed on less relevant and (controversially) unhelpful techniques when applied
     specifically to standards.</li>
   </ul></p>
  <p>This short book was written in DITA using an XML editor called oXygen Author. It was easy to
   write using DITA, but it made me aware of DITA's limitations too. Let's explore how DITA might,
   or might not help you to write policy and procedure standards documents..</p>
  <p> </p>
 </conbody>
</concept>
