<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_gpb_hwf_23">
 <title>Introduction</title>
 <shortdesc>Structured documents provide the best, simplest and most reliable tools to write policy and procedure documents.</shortdesc>
 <prolog>
  <author>John Gordon Tait</author>
  <copyright>
   <copyryear year="2012"/>
   <copyrholder>John Gordon Tait</copyrholder>
  </copyright>
 </prolog>
 <conbody>
  <p>This book is written for someone writing or managing policy and procedure documents, and
   standards documents of any kind. (I use these terms interchangeably.)</p>
  <p>These documents are usually managed by small dedicated teams. The content comes from experts in
   their fields. These subject matter experts usually don't care too much about documentation
   because their expertise lies in other areas.</p>
  <p>Can the technology and technique called DITA help? Well, perhaps.</p>
  <p>There are some very real advantages to trying DITA for this purpose, and some real problems. If
   you are involved in managing standards, I think it could be well worth trying, but the existing
   literature seems to be written by<ul id="ul_tdm_4xr_h3">
    <li>originators and implementators of the DITA specification, who are perhaps not aware of the
     specific needs of <i>standards</i> authors</li>
    <li>consultants of various kinds, who might emphasise some of the benefits and less of the
     disadvantages, and who also might try to solve unnecessary technical problems</li>
    <li>technical writers in the specific fields of product documentation and, more especially,
     computer software documentation. This is quite a different genre from standards, and might be
     focussed on irrelevant and (controversially) unhelpful techniques.</li>
   </ul></p>
  <p>This short book was written in DITA using an XML editor called oXygen Author. It was easy to
   write using DITA, but it made me aware of DITA's limitations too. Let's explore how DITA might,
   or might not help you to write policy and procedure standards documents..</p>
  <p> </p>
 </conbody>
</concept>
