<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="task_o4x_sw3_f3">
    <title>Looking at XML (for technical authors)</title>
    <shortdesc>XML has its roots as a document markup language. Nevertheless, it's not pretty and
        you'll need an XML editor to ease your eyes from the angle brackets and to avoid typing
        closing element tags.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
        <author>John Gordon Tait</author>
        <copyright>
            <copyryear year="2012"/>
            <copyrholder>John Gordon Tait</copyrholder>
        </copyright>
    </prolog>
    <taskbody>
        <section>
            <title>oXygen Author is a deservedly popular XML editor</title>
            <p>Using an XML editor like oXygen can be unsettling for a technical author. There are
                many open windows displaying lots of technical options.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, I would resist using a <i>Word</i>-based tool or any other tools that
                purportedly makes the author's life easier.</p>
            <p>At times, it's simpler to drop into the raw XML when the editor doesn't behave as
                expected, or it's just simpler. For example, editing file extensions in DITA maps is
                much easier using the Text view rather than the Author view.</p>
            <p>The existing literature also assumes a solid IT support network.</p>
            <p>Instead, it's worth considering oXygen as a nuclear-powered <i>Word</i> processor
                that can be used as a stand-alone application to get things done. It can produce
                web-sites and documents.</p>
            <p>The one caveat is that, in order to conditionally-filter content, you're going to
                have to specialise the DITA open toolkit. This means edit a few lines in a text
                file, and create a new text file as well. It's not pleasant, but it's useful because
                you can them filter out content to suit. This can minimise the number of actual
                files you need to maintain.</p>
            <p>DITA proponents will stress topicising into small topics, when in fact it makes
                managing things harder. Conditional text is one idea that DITA really gets right,
                becuase it <i>reduces </i> the number of files you'll ned to manage.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Getting oXygen Author</title>
            <p>At the time of writing, oXygen is available on a cheap academic/personal license. The
                SyncRO Soft team are also happy to send a no-charge time-limited license. I've also
                found the Syncro Soft team very helpful in responding dorectliy to techincal
                queries.</p>
            <p>Oxygen works with Windows and Ubuntu (I've tried both, and the license permits this.)
                and more. For some reason, I was able to install oXygen on a Windows work laptop
                without the usual administrator rights prompts.</p>
            <p>There are two other versions of oXygen, but Author is the one to get for writing.
                It's got Author mode, comes integrated with the DITA-OT, and doesn't have too many
                unnecessary developer features that'll make you feel like a noob forever.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Use a programmer's text editor like Emacs for small edits and corrections</title>
            <p>It's also useful to edit topic unrelated to the main project that you're working on,
                as the opened file won't get jumbled with your project files in oXygen.</p>
        </section>
    </taskbody>
</task>
