<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="task_oyp_3wf_23">
    <title>Naming files and folders</title>
    <shortdesc>Give special attention to the names of files and folders. These will be used in your
        maps, and with allow your maps to be read like tables of contents, making your work much
        easier.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
        <metadata>
            <keywords>
                <indexterm>naming<indexterm>files</indexterm><indexterm>folders</indexterm></indexterm>
                <indexterm>folders<indexterm>naming</indexterm></indexterm>
                <indexterm>files<indexterm>naming</indexterm></indexterm>
                <indexterm/>
            </keywords>
        </metadata>
    </prolog>
    <taskbody>
        <section>
            <title>Use lower case rather than upper case and use the underscore character rather
                than a space</title>
            <p>Use lower case except when it would be perverse not to do so, e.g. in organization
                names.</p>
            <p>For example, the name of the source file for this DITA topic is
                    <codeph>naming_files_and_folders.xml</codeph>.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Put legacy structurall features at the end of titles, in brackets</title>
            <p>In migration projectjs, it's quite possible that you will want to keep a record of
                original titles. This might help to to complte a migration, or it might help
                existing readers who are used to referring to a document called "PROC 1234", or an
                appendix called "Appendix A".</p>
            <p>Try to be helpful to your readers.</p>
            <p>For example, as a topic title or the title of a map.</p>
            <lq>How to clear a spill (PROC 1234)</lq>
            <p>For example, in an appendix:</p>
            <lq>How to apply for a deviation (Appendix A)</lq>
            <p>This has the triple purpose of:<ul id="ul_icl_f1x_f3">
                    <li>deprecating these structural elements, when all you really want to worry
                        about is topic title and maps</li>
                    <li>maintain a record of where the topic or section element came from, visible
                        even in the map (for topcv titles)</li>
                    <li>allowing you to quietly drop the strucral element in the future withour
                        significantly altering the title</li>
                </ul></p>
        </section>
    </taskbody>
</task>
