<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="task_gd3_xlb_f3">
    <title>Related techniques and technologies to DITA and what you can learn from them</title>
    <shortdesc>It's worth lookng at precursors to DITA and what they where for. There are related
        subject such as minimalism, the Hughes Aircraft STOP report, and Edmund Weiss' computer
        documentation books.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
        <author>John Gordon Tait</author>
        <copyright>
            <copyryear year="2012"/>
            <copyrholder>John Gordon Tait</copyrholder>
        </copyright>
    </prolog>
    <taskbody>
        <section>
            <title>Comparing the methodologies</title>
            <table frame="all" id="table_fj3_5dx_f3">
                <title>Compring the methodologies</title>
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Publication</entry>
                            <entry>What's useful</entry>
                            <entry>What's less useful and not useful</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>STOP</entry>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry>Scissors and wall technique</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Weiss computer docs</entry>
                            <entry>Relates John Carolls' minimalism to topic based writing
                                directly</entry>
                            <entry>COmputer documentation tradition</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry morerows="1">standards house style</entry>
                            <entry>Mature consultation process. Have format review meetings. </entry>
                            <entry>BSI and ISO sell bif documents for a living. Process generates
                                large. documents</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Well understood house style</entry>
                            <entry>Wedded to standard expository model, with a broadly scoped
                                documents split into nested subsections.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Org-mode</title>
            <p>The Emacs text edior </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>LaTex and LyX</title>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>GNU texinfo</title>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>LibreOffice</title>
            <p>LibreOffice (and its cousin, OpenOffice) has a conditional text feature than
                <i>Word</i> just doesn't have.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Help authoring tools</title>
            <p>If you are from the computer documentation tradition, it's likely that you have used
                or at least heard of the "help authoring tools". If not, it's unlikely that you've
                come across them.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Using Word and PDF documents in a modular way</title>
            <p>The STOP report was a modular technique that didn't use technology at all. The
                collaboration technique was a wall, and it worked very well. Therefore, it's
                possible to undertake a modular approach using your exisitng tools.</p>
            <p>In fact, if you create a series of short self-contained documents, each with a
                helpful headline style title and a useful thesis sentence, you can create a very
                good basis for managing procedure and policy documentation. It is easy to, say,
                convert  <i>Word </i> documents written this way to PDF using Adobe <i>Writer</i>,
                and compile the PDF documents into custom manuals as required. You can mange the
                source <i>Word</i> documents and PDF outputs using your existing systems. You can,
                this way, get much of the value of using DITA with none of the learning curves
                associated with learning XML mark up and new kinds of software.</p>
            <p>One main hurdle why this isn't likely to be as successful as it might appear is
                cultural rather than technological. People simply aren't used to using <i>Word</i>
                this way. There's almost an expectation that <i>Word</i> documents need to be big,
                divided down into sections and subsections, and cross-referenced--this is almost the
                mark of a serious, respectable <i>Word</i> document. Couple this with the tradtional
                BSI/ISO standards model, and you might find that it's too hard to manage authors
                this way. <i>Word</i> has simply been around too long.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Very useful documentation</title>
        </section>
        
        
    </taskbody>
</task>
