<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="task_ov2_kzj_f3">
    <title>3. Using content references</title>
    <shortdesc>Use content references to manage lists of terms and definitions.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
        <author>John Gordon Tait</author>
        <copyright>
            <copyryear year="2012"/>
            <copyrholder>John Gordon Tait</copyrholder>
        </copyright>
    </prolog>
    <taskbody>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction to content references</title>
            <p>I think content references ("conrefs") are DITA's killer feature. This is very
                powerful and is probably a "killer feature".</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Are lists of terms and definitions actually needed?</title>
            <p>Don't add abbreviations to these lists.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What to conref</title>
            <p>You can conref whole <codeph>section</codeph> elements. This probably isn't te
                canonical way of using conrefs, because the computer documentation tradition seems
                to require much more of the alteration of sentence and meaning rather than pulling
                whole paragraphs across.</p>
            <p>For standards, this mechanism allows simple and predictable transclusion for smallish
                packets of text, with might or might not have titles.</p>
            <p>Conref <codeph>phrase</codeph> elements.</p>
            <p><codeph>Resource-only</codeph> attribute</p>
            <p>6 DITA content references – tutorial: how to manage a centralised glossary I'll
                demonstrate how conrefs can be helpful in producing policy and procedure documents.
                These kind of documents can typically have a life of three years.</p>
            <p>This is short enough that they might not warrant publishing professionally, but long
                enough that they will be referred to by other documents, and eventually be
                cannibalised by successor documents. One typical casuality of this arrangement is
                the lack of a consistent list of organisational terms and definitions.</p>
            <p>It's just hard to keep everything current with this kind of churn. Conrefs can help
                manage these. Rather than copy or write terms and definitions in a document, they
                could be held in a DITA glossary topic reserved for this purpose, called
                "glossary_bank.dita". It could be hundreds of entries long.</p>
            <p>Global glossary: &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> &lt;!DOCTYPE glossgroup
                PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Glossary Group//EN" "glossgroup.dtd"> &lt;glossgroup
                id="gemstone_glossary"> &lt;title>Bank of gemstone terms and definitions&lt;/title>
                &lt;glossentry id="diamond"> &lt;glossterm>diamond&lt;/glossterm>
                &lt;glossdef>gemstone, clear and colourless with renowned physical properties, that
                is a metastable allotrope of carbon&lt;/glossdef> &lt;/glossentry> &lt;glossentry
                id="emerald"> &lt;glossterm>emerald&lt;/glossterm> &lt;glossdef>gemstone, coloured
                green by trace amounts of chromium and sometimes vanadium, that is a variety of the
                mineral beryl&lt;/glossdef> &lt;/glossentry> &lt;glossentry id="ruby">
                &lt;glossterm>ruby&lt;/glossterm> &lt;glossdef>gemstone, coloured pink to blood-red,
                that is a variety of the mineral corundum (aluminium oxide)&lt;/glossdef>
                &lt;/glossentry> &lt;glossentry id="sapphire"> &lt;glossterm>sapphire&lt;/glossterm>
                &lt;glossdef>gemstone, coloured blue, yellow, pink, purple, orange, or greenish by
                trace amounts of elements such as iron, titanium, chromium, copper, or magnesium,
                that is a variety of the mineral corundum (aluminium oxide)&lt;/glossdef>
                &lt;/glossentry> &lt;/glossgroup></p>
            <p>This is our global list for use throughout the organisation. A map for a document
                would include this bank as a resource-only topic. Our map could then contain another
                glossary. This second glossary pulls the required terms over from the global
                bank.</p>
            <p>The main advantage here is that the glossary bank can be shared with all documents.
                Corrections made to the glossary bank will feed through to all documents. When
                writing a document, you can just pick the term you want from the bank and you will
                be confident that it's correct and up to date. I'm using another glossary topic
                (rather than pull the terms directly into a, say, task topic) because glossentry
                elements belong to the glossgroup topic specialisation. Our glossary, using a conref
                to pull the emerald and the ruby terms from the glossary bank: &lt;?xml
                version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> &lt;!DOCTYPE glossgroup PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA
                Glossary Group//EN" "glossgroup.dtd"> &lt;glossgroup
                id="cut_gemstones_glossary_using_conrefs"> &lt;title>Glossary for this cut gemstones
                specification&lt;/title> &lt;glossentry id="emerald_in_manual"
                conref="glossary_bank.dita#emerald"> &lt;glossterm/>&lt;/glossentry> &lt;glossentry
                id="ruby_in_manual" conref="glossary_bank.dita#ruby">
                &lt;glossterm/>&lt;/glossentry> &lt;/glossgroup> Map, containing the following: the
                glossary bank, marked as "resource-only" (so we don't render it) our manual's
                glossary, which pulls over two terms ("emerald" and "ruby") using conrefs the
                emerald and ruby topics a relationship table, which will allow the reader to jump
                between the two topics. &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> &lt;!DOCTYPE map
                PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Map//EN" "map.dtd"> &lt;map chunk="by-document
                to-content"> &lt;title>Glossary tutorial&lt;/title> &lt;topicref
                href="glossary_bank.dita" processing-role="resource-only"/> &lt;topicref
                href="glossary.dita"/> &lt;topicref href="requirements_for_emeralds.dita"/>
                &lt;topicref href="requirements_for_rubies.dita"/> &lt;reltable title="Cut gemstone
                specification"> &lt;relheader> &lt;relcolspec/> &lt;relcolspec/> &lt;/relheader>
                &lt;relrow> &lt;relcell> &lt;topicref href="requirements_for_emeralds.dita"/>
                &lt;/relcell> &lt;relcell> &lt;topicref href="requirements_for_rubies.dita"/>
                &lt;/relrow> &lt;/reltable> &lt;/map> The "requirements_for_emeralds.dita" topic
                looks like this. (The ruby topic is its equivalent.) I added a cross-reference. DITA
                practitioners generally don't like cross-references, preferring to use relationship
                tables exclusively (which link topics together and where the links are usually
                rendered at the end of their topics). I usually agree with this, but topics
                containing long lists might be better served by links to the item rather than the
                whole topic. &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> &lt;!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC
                "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "task.dtd"> &lt;task
                id="requirements_emeralds"> &lt;title>Requirements for cut emeralds&lt;/title>
                &lt;shortdesc>All cut emeralds are required to conform to this
                standard.&lt;/shortdesc> &lt;taskbody> &lt;section>&lt;title>Introduction&lt;/title>
                &lt;p>Here is the specification for a cut &lt;xref
                href="glossary.dita#emerald_in_manual"/>.&lt;/p> &lt;/section> &lt;/taskbody>
                &lt;/task> Files Cut gemstone requirements with glossary</p>
            <p>Psychic editing using DITA's conref push</p>
            <p>Normal conref allows you to pull text in from a resource. Conref push works in
                reverse, and allows you to push your new text into existing content without
                modifying that content!</p>
            <p>You can modify text without going anywhere near it! It's like telekinesis. There are
                untold uses for this magic.</p>
            <p>Map: &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> &lt;!DOCTYPE map PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD
                DITA Map//EN" "map.dtd"> &lt;map chunk="by-document to-content"> &lt;title>Doctor
                Who test&lt;/title> &lt;topicref href="doctor_who_subject.ditamap" format="ditamap"
                type="subjectScheme"/> &lt;topicref href="first_serials.dita"/> &lt;topicref
                href="resources.dita" processing-role="resource-only"/> &lt;/map> Here's the
                original text. Note that you do need id numbers to give the conref push feature
                something to look for: &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> &lt;!DOCTYPE topic
                PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> &lt;topic id="web">
                &lt;title>List of First Doctor serials&lt;/title> &lt;body> &lt;section>
                &lt;title>The Web Planet&lt;/title> &lt;p id="here">This is a peculiar story. There
                are no humanoid monsters. The &lt;ph id="target"/>Zarbi runs into the camera.&lt;/p>
                &lt;/section> &lt;/body> &lt;/topic> The text renders to this: List of First Doctor
                serials The Web Planet This is a peculiar story. There are no humanoid monsters. The
                Zarbi runs into the camera. Okay. I'm going to modify this beautiful passage wih
                conref push.</p>
            <p>This is the resource: &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> &lt;!DOCTYPE topic
                PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> &lt;topic id="bank">
                &lt;title>Resources&lt;/title> &lt;body> &lt;p conaction="pushbefore">Here's the
                facts.&lt;/p> &lt;p conaction="mark" conref="first_serials.dita#web/here">&lt;/p>
                &lt;p>&lt;ph conaction="pushbefore">bloody &lt;/ph>&lt;/p> &lt;p>&lt;ph
                conaction="mark" conref="first_serials.dita#web/target">&lt;/ph>&lt;/p> &lt;p
                conaction="mark" conref="first_serials.dita#web/here">&lt;/p> &lt;p
                conaction="pushafter">And those were the facts.&lt;/p> &lt;/body> &lt;/topic> </p>
            <p>These pieces are injected into the original text. The original file does not change.
                New rendering of the text: </p>
        </section>
    </taskbody>
</task>
