<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="task_ov2_kzj_f3">
    <title>Using content references</title>
    <shortdesc>DITA's content references ("conrefs") allow you to pull small pieces of text from a
        topic into another topic. This is very powerful and is probably a "killer feature". </shortdesc>
    <prolog>
        <author>John Gordon Tait</author>
        <copyright>
            <copyryear year="2012-2013"/>
            <copyrholder>John Gordon Tait</copyrholder>
        </copyright>
    </prolog>
    <taskbody>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction to content references</title>
            <p>Conrefs are used when you want to reuse pieces of text or other material from a topic
                in another topic. As long as the content reference pulls in an element that would
                ordinarily be allowed if it was written the topic directly (and you give it an
                    <codeph>id</codeph> number), you can pull elements over rather than using
                cutting and pasting.</p>
            <p>This is very useful for keeping consistency in your standards material. If material
                is pasted over between traditional documents, the connection between the documents
                is lost at that point. It is very easy to modify one of the documents and not
                another. The content will diverge over time even if it is meant to be the same.</p>
            <p>To avoid creating a kind of spaghetti, it is a good idea to create topics designed as
                a resource banks for conrefs. If one resource topic is included in a topic map, you
                identify this bank as <codeph>resource-only</codeph>, meaning it will not appear in
                the rendered output, except where its material is used in a content reference in
                another topic.</p>
            <p>Examples for this in standards are:<ul id="ul_fbc_zjk_hj">
                    <li>a bank of terms and definitions</li>
                    <li>standard "boilerplate" text that is supposed to be the same in all
                        standards</li>
                    <li>any chunk of text that is smaller than a topic but can be used as a block,
                        e.g. a commonly used figure that has a title, an image and some notes under
                        it.</li>
                </ul></p>
            <p>You can conref whole <codeph>section</codeph> elements (where these elements are
                used). This probably isn't the canonical way of using conrefs, but it is easy and
                convenient.</p>
            <p>Even small groups of words can be used in a conref: wrapping a
                    <codeph>phrase</codeph> element around words and using conref to pull it across
                allows you to modify a sentence. The advantage to this is that if the
                    <codeph>phrase</codeph> element changes in the resouce bank, you will change the
                word in all of your content when it is rendered.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Example creating a glossary</title>
            <p>I'll demonstrate how conrefs can be helpful in producing policy and procedure
                documents. Standards have, say, a life of three years. This is short enough that
                they might not warrant publishing professionally, but long enough that they will be
                referred to by other documents, and eventually be cannibalised by successor
                documents. One typical casualty of this arrangement is the lack of a consistent list
                of organisational terms and definitions.</p>
            <p>It's hard to keep everything current with this kind of churn using traditional
                documents. Conrefs can help manage these.</p>
            <p>Rather than copy or write terms and definitions in a document, they could be held in
                a DITA glossary topic reserved for this purpose, called "glossary_bank.dita". It
                could be hundreds of entries long and would be a global list for use throughout the
                organisation.</p>
            <p>A map for a document would include this bank as a resource-only topic. Our map could
                then contain another glossary. This second glossary pulls the required terms over
                from the global bank using a conref.</p>
            <p>The main advantage is that the glossary bank can be shared with all documents.
                Corrections and updates made to the glossary bank will feed through to all
                documents. When writing a document, you can just pick the term you want from the
                bank and you will be confident that it's correct and up to date.</p>
            <p>(You would use another glossary topic rather than pull the terms directly into a
                different kind of topic because glossentry elements belong to the glossgroup topic
                specialisation, and this approach is necessary to work within DITA's own rules.)</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Conref push: content references in reverse</title>
            <p>Normal conref allows you to pull text in from a resource. Conref push works in
                reverse, and allows you to push new text into existing content without modifying
                that DITA content.</p>
            <p>You can render different versions of text without modifying the topic that it is
                based on. An example of where this is useful is injecting text into templates. The
                template does not change but you could push titles, dates and organisational
                information into it and include this in your map. The template can be kept
                secure.</p>
            <p> </p>
        </section>
    </taskbody>
</task>
