<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="task_ckg_pjy_f3">
    <title>Writing standards on a structured way</title>
    <shortdesc>Structure can mean the assembly of documents from small building blocks called
        "topics", and also a consistent internal structure using a text mark-up
        language.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
        <author>John Gordon Tait</author>
        <copyright>
            <copyryear year="2012"/>
            <copyrholder>John Gordon Tait</copyrholder>
        </copyright>
    </prolog>
    <taskbody>
        <section>
            <title>Mark up separates meaning from presentation</title>
            <p>As well as writing in mark up (where the effects of the mark up might not be very
                apparent), you will also have little direct control of the appearance of the output.
                This includes important aspects line page breaks and the appearance of tables.</p>
            <p>It can be difficult to adjust to this, particulary when you are used to having easy
                control of document presentation with a word processor, and especially when the
                output is <i>less</i> satisfactory than you can acheive with one.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, after time, it does become much simpler to just open a map and start
                work without being bothered by page layout, margins, and font size.</p>
            <p>In DITA, there is still some presentational structure to consider. Italics and bold
                are there, and images need to be given a (e.g <codeph>width</codeph>) size for PDF
                output (or they can spill over the page). It's still much, much less than you will
                find with a word processor.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, It's easy to emphasise how you or your writers will spend less time
                worrying about structure and more time worrying about appearance. In fact, DITA
                users are very interested in the appearance of their documents.</p>
            <p>You can have some direct control of the appearance of XHTML output (and by extention
                EPUB and oXygen's WebHelp by configuring the appearance with cascading style sheets
                (CSS). CSS provides a template-like way of altering the appearance. It's fairly easy
                to learn the basics (the web is not short of CSS tutorials) and it's well integrated
                woth DITA and oXygen.</p>
            <p>PDF output is much, much harder to customise. You can add some images to flag up
                parts of text in conditional processing, but that's about it for the DITA-OT unless
                you are or can call upon the skills of a developer.</p>
            <p>Large Word documents are unwieldly, inconsistent, and tend to die after 50 pages.</p>
            <p>A real problem with Word documents is that they just don't scale. There's many way to
                achieve the same thing.</p>
            
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Authors can use different <i>Word</i> template and can have different
                styles</title>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Authors manage sequential numbering as well as the content and appearance</title>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Structural writing means the <i>computer</i> takes some of the strain</title>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Write upward from small parts rather than divide downwards</title>
            <p>A document written from the bottom up can <i>look</i> similar to a document split
                into sections and subsections ("clauses" and "subclauses" in standards), but they
                are quite different regarding their maintainabilty and (less visibly but not less
                true), sometimes their ability to be understood by their reader.</p>
            <p>(STOP technique)</p>
        </section>
    </taskbody>
</task>
