<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="task_ijp_rwd_f3">
    <title>Working groups</title>
    <shortdesc>Policy and procedure documents are often written by working groups composed of
        subject matter experts ("SMEs"). Even if you are responsible for writing the content,
        putting working groups together is the most effective way of getting correct
        content. Unlike computer help or product information, policy and procedure documents will
        almost always need to be formally reviewed.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
        <author>John Gordon Tait</author>
        <copyright>
            <copyryear year="2012"/>
            <copyrholder>John Gordon Tait</copyrholder>
        </copyright>
    </prolog>
    <taskbody>
        <section>
            <title>Use a large screen of a projector to permit authors to focus on the actual
                content</title>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Resist the temptation to discuss content by email</title>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Bring the documents along to short, informal meetings</title>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Send out a comments form to allow compilation of comments and prevent annotated
                drafts</title>
            <p>Reviewers (sometimes called stakeholders) can't really be expected to understand DITA
                code or work within a content management system. The <i>ad hoc</i> nature of
                standards, which means that new writers are always involved, is amplified when
                stakeholders are involved. New stakeholders will probably be uninterested.</p>
            <p>Possibly the simplest way to review a standard is to circulate a draft PDF with an
                editable comments form. Comments forms can be easily collated (with comments
                arranged by clause number, etc.) to allow them to be reviewed in sequence.</p>
            <p>This isn't any different from the conventional way of drafting standards, i.e. the
                underlying DITA code ought to be invisible to the reader.</p>
            <p>If the authors and stakeholders are drawn from the same small team, it might be
                achievable to get a technological solution working instead, but in practice it'd
                be better to drop the barrier to entry as low as possible for the stakeholders to get as many
                contributions as possible.</p>
        </section>
    </taskbody>
</task>
